<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Jacobite principles vindicated in answer to a letter sent to the author. Dedicated to the Queen of England.</title>
            <author>Lawton, Charlwood, 1660-1721.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88839</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L739C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215013</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899527</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899527</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154028</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88839)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154028)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2394:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Jacobite principles vindicated in answer to a letter sent to the author. Dedicated to the Queen of England.</title>
                  <author>Lawton, Charlwood, 1660-1721.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Re-printed at London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year 1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Charlwood Lawton.</note>
                  <note>Pp. 17-19 misnumbered 19, 17-18.</note>
                  <note>Copy filmed at UMI microfilm Early English Books 1641-1700 reel 2394 has pages cropped with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1689-1702 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154028:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154028:1"/>
            <p>THE Jacobite Principles VINDICATED, In Anſwer to a LETTER ſent to the AUTHOR.</p>
            <p>DEDICATED TO THE QUEEN OF ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>Re-printed at <hi>London</hi> in the year 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:154028:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154028:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the QUEEN.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Beſeech Your Majeſty's Pardon, that, without firſt conſulting You, I lay at the <hi>Royal Feet of a moſt Injur'd Queen</hi> the Vindication of a <hi>moſt Injur'd Party;</hi> and I hope this Dedication will have ſo much Effect upon the <hi>Publick,</hi> as to ſatisfie the World of my Candor in repreſenting the Meaſures of Your Majeſties, and the <hi>Notions</hi> of thoſe that are in Your Intereſt; for it cannot be ſuppoſed I dare inſcribe that to Your Name, that is contrary to the <hi>Royal Intentions</hi> of <hi>His Majeſty</hi> and <hi>Your Self.</hi> I muſt confeſs I think I have reaſon rather to beg Pardon that I have not ſufficiently explained the good Inc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <hi>You both</hi> have to make us Happy. I chooſe to put Your Majeſties Name before theſe Sheets, rather than the <hi>King</hi>'s, (though I ſuddenly deſign to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate a ſhort Diſcourſe to Him) becauſe, if poſſible, the World has been more maliciouſly Unjuſt and Inveterate towards YOU, than ever againſt HIM; nay, ſome have preſum'd to cenſure Your Majeſty for thoſe Errors and Miſtakes of His Reign (for which I don't pretend to apologize) which were entirely the Work of His <hi>Falſe</hi> and <hi>Corrupted Miniſters:</hi> and yet I have heard from thoſe who had Opportunity to know, and who are not much Your Friends, that <hi>Publick Affairs</hi> were not Your Concern whilſt His Majeſtly was here; which is the more to be admired and applauded in Your Majeſty, ſince all that had the Honour to wait upon You about Buſineſs when His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's abſence in <hi>Ireland</hi> made it abſolutely neceſſary for You to apply Your Self to it, found in Your Majeſty a <hi>Genius</hi> fitted to all Great Affairs. And, <hi>Madam,</hi> tho' You retired, as ſoon as the <hi>King</hi> return'd to St <hi>Germains,</hi> purely to the exerciſe of Your own private Virtues; yet I am ſo aſſur'd that the Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons You then made, whilſt You was perfectly forced to look into the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Affairs, and ſince You have entirely quitted them to His Majeſty's Care, have fully convinc'd You that theſe are the proper Meaſures of Accommodation, that I don't doubt but Your Majeſty will graciouſly forgive my Preſumption.</p>
            <p>I know few Men approach <hi>Crown'd Heads</hi> without making <hi>Panegyricks;</hi> but I ſhall not enter upon a <hi>Theme</hi> upon which <hi>Poſterity</hi> will better bear Juſt Things to be ſaid than the <hi>preſent Age</hi> will yet; nor is a Courtly Stile my Talent, tho' it is from a ſenſe of Your Goodneſs as well as Greatneſs that I am devoted to Your Commands and Intereſt.</p>
            <p>I have heard of but ſew Faults that any Party has found with the Firſt Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Paper, which I hope is a good ſign that all Men are at laſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to moderate Things. I am ſure it was written with all the good mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing imaginable towards my King and Country, Your Majeſty and Poſterity, and all the ſeveral divided <hi>Parties</hi> of Your <hi>Subjects:</hi> And that YOU may be <hi>Glorious,</hi> and They <hi>Happy,</hi> is the conſtant Prayer, and ſhall be the Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your MAJESTY,</salute>
               <signed>Your Majeſties moſt Obedient Subject, and Faithful Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:154028:3"/>
            <head>THE Jacobite Principles Vindicated.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS much as Engliſh-men have been famed for their Hearts, they have been always re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached for their Heads. They have always loſt their Wits by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oxications. They have been always a tempeſtuous, a heady, and a divided People: But they never were more apparently ſo, than they have been in this laſt <hi>Change.</hi> They have not only out-run their <hi>Own,</hi> but the Pretences of their <hi>Deliverer.</hi> He came not for a Crown, but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs our Grievances; but we would give the Crown, yet neglect our Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, and all Amendment of our Conſtitution: And we will ſtill main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain our <hi>Injuſtice</hi> in the one, and <hi>Folly</hi> in the other. Thoſe that reſolve to do ſo, may ſee <hi>Maeſtricht</hi> taken after <hi>Mons</hi> and <hi>Namur, Flande<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſubmitted to <hi>France,</hi> the Confederacy broken, and we (divided as we are, and ſhall be, amongſt our ſelves) left to grapple with all that Power, which has now for four Years employed ſuch united Forces. Nor can we hope God will work a Miracle to ſupport ſo unjuſt a Quarrel. They may ſee all this War brought into our own Bowels, into this divided Kingdom; may ſee it make Havock and Deſolation upon this Iſland; in a word, may ſee Friends and Kindred killing and deſtroving one another, embruing their Hands in each others Blood; and then our pretended Fears may become true, thoſe Miſeries overtake us, with the pretended Suſpicions of which we have coloured over and countenanced our <hi>unrighteous Doings.</hi> But you think it is too late to or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w back, and you can ſee no ſecurity in the <hi>Reſtoration;</hi> you can't ſee our <hi>Lives,</hi> and our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> our <hi>Liberty,</hi> and our <hi>Property</hi> will be ſafe. I averr you impoſe upon your ſelf, and one Man impoſes upon another. But you ſay you are frighted at the Diſcourſes of ſome, both <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> and <hi>Catholick, Jacobites.</hi> You ſay they talk for <hi>Slavery,</hi> and that when we are <hi>Slaves,</hi> we may be made <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Yet if you would conſider, you have been invited by publiſhed Pamphlets to reflect who among the <hi>Jacobites</hi> are likely to give you ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. Would you have Men ſet their Names to what they write? There are Men that you believe are in King <hi>James</hi>'s Intereſt, that you have no reaſon to believe would ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice their <hi>Country</hi> or their <hi>Religion,</hi> and that I aſſure you have as true a love for thoſe good things you men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as you can have your ſelf, and that would joyn with you and any Engliſh-men, to ask in a reſpectful manner for every honeſt thing that is neceſſary to ſecure us from <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> and the <hi>Violence</hi> of all ſorts of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and that are themſelves ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and can authentically ſatisfie
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:154028:3"/>you that the <hi>King</hi> has been a long time willing to make all thoſe neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Conceſſions that will ſecure the <hi>Church of England,</hi> as the <hi>Eſtabliſhed Worſhip,</hi> make an <hi>Impartial Toleration</hi> ſafe, and for the future put our <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties</hi> and <hi>Property</hi> out of the Power (as much as good and wholſom Laws can do it) of <hi>Male-adminiſtration;</hi> nay, that are ſatisfied he muſt be willing to do ſo if ever he will come home. There are <hi>Jacobites</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what <hi>Gourville</hi> is related to have once ſaid concerning our Kings; <hi>Qu'n Roy d'Angleterre qui veut eſtre l'Homme de ſon Peuple, eſt le plus Grand Roy du Monde, mais s'il veut eſtre quel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que choſe d'avantage par Dieu, il n'est plus Rien.</hi> There are <hi>Jacobites</hi> that are for Reformations, though they believe them more laſting under un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conteſted Titles than where Title is too great a part of the Diſpute; that think it Lawful for <hi>Kings,</hi> and their <hi>Parliaments,</hi> to limit and explain the Nature of <hi>Prerogatives,</hi> though they think it ſafer to the Conſtitution to leave it to the <hi>three Eſtates</hi> ſo to do, than for one or two of them to inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate too rudely without the Conſent of the other; that own a great Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the Changing or Abolition of ſome particular Laws, and altering Fundamentals. And the greateſt Aſſertors of <hi>Liberty</hi> muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that <hi>Prerogatives</hi> in <hi>Kings,</hi> ſuitable to the Reſpective Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are neceſſary to maintain thoſe Conſtitutions, and to protect their <hi>Subjects,</hi> and conſequently that in all Pacts and Compoſitions their People make with them, due care ſhould be taken even by the People, not to take from their <hi>Kings</hi> any <hi>eſſential Powers. Prerogative,</hi> like a River, ſometimes gains, and ſometimes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes in its Banks; but the Balk of the Community ſails ſafeſt when it keeps its own Natural Channel, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the reſpective Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>Bacon,</hi> that writes the Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of the Government of <hi>England,</hi> is certainly no over Monarchical Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor; yet he has this Expreſſion in relation to King <hi>Stephen: Too much Counter-ſecurity from the King to the People, is like too many Covenants in Marriage, that make room for Jealouſy, and are but Seeds of an unquiet Life.</hi> After all, it is certainly the Nature of Engliſh-men to delight in, and they have been uſed to a <hi>Limited, Explained,</hi> and <hi>Hereditary Monarchy;</hi> and <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram licet expellas furca tamen ipſa recur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat,</hi> will be found true in a <hi>Politick,</hi> as well as a <hi>Natural Senſe,</hi> by all thoſe who would change our Government into an <hi>Abſolute Monarchy</hi> or <hi>Downright Democracy,</hi> or that will interrupt the Succeſſion. The <hi>Lancaſtrian</hi> Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the Late Times, witneſs this. But perhaps ſome of theſe <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobites</hi> you complain of, may think to diſgrace what I have ſaid, by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling theſe Notions <hi>Republican.</hi> To theſe Gentlement I will firſt Anſwer, That ſince we are ſo Elemented for a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth,</hi> there is no keeping it out but by a Reformation of the <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> that may as apparently Anſwer all the Reaſons why Government was firſt depoſited in the Magiſtrates hands, either by God, or the People. I will not diſpute the Original of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment at this time, but I will offer one thing to theſe <hi>Speculators</hi> to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of, which is, That whilſt they too much cajole Kings, they loſe their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154028:4"/>Intereſt with the People, and miſlead an <hi>Engliſh Monarch,</hi> and make way for that Government both in Church and State, which they would (if they underſtood how) oppoſe. They help the Real Common-wealths men to Arguments, and give the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> opportunity to inſinuate, and gain the Hearts of the People. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps were the People of <hi>England</hi> a <hi>Prima Materia,</hi> I would be very well content that the Draughts of theſe ſuperfine <hi>Projectors</hi> ſhould be debated, but I think <hi>Machiavel</hi> was as good a Politician as moſt of Them; and yet he ſays, <hi>If the Variations of Times are not obſerved, and Laws and Cuſtoms al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered accordingly, much Miſchief muſt follow.</hi> And in another Place, he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms it <hi>a very had Thing to keep them in Servitude, who are diſpoſed to be Free.</hi> And whoever has reflected upon the extravagant Courſes we have taken to be ſo, ever ſince the Beginning of the late Civil Wars, cannot ſure doubt of our Diſpoſition: For tho we have been miſtaken in our <hi>Cures,</hi> no body can be miſtaken in our <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſity.</hi> I am no Lord, nor ever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire or hope for any Title. I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſerve my Country in the <hi>Lower</hi> than the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper-Houſe;</hi> and if my Country never thinks fit to ſend me to <hi>that</hi> neither, I ſhall never <hi>Court,</hi> much leſs <hi>Bribe,</hi> for that Imployment from my Country: for I would not be Bribed in it. Yet conſidering how much the Power of the <hi>Lords</hi> has in ſome Reigns been a check to the <hi>Incroachment</hi> of Kings, and in others to the <hi>hot-headedneſs</hi> of the People, I ſhould be willing to ſcrew up the <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocratical</hi> part of our Government, though not to the heighth it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times has had in our Policy: but the preſent Ferments of <hi>England</hi> make it impracticable. And tho ſome Men are, I am not for driving Nails that will not go; when we may without breach of Conſcience let that Work alone to a more <hi>cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſighted Age.</hi> Though I think our <hi>Oaths,</hi> and the <hi>Original Contract</hi> of our Law Books, bind us to reſtore the <hi>King;</hi> yet I know no Obligation we lie under to reſtore Power to the Lords, but as there ſhall appear both great Feaſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Expediency: I am not for hazarding much for bringing things exactly and minutely to my <hi>Platform.</hi> It will be always enough for me, if the Fundamentals of our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are preſerved. A <hi>Trimmer in Politicks,</hi> if it means one that would avoid Extremities, and compoſe Things, and not one that ſerves himſelf by all Times and Changes, is a Name and Character that I ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways revere. But to give theſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen a farther Anſwer, I muſt tell them, that it is plain, by undeniable Matter of Fact, that to thoſe Perſons that ingaged in the <hi>Scotch</hi> Plot, tho he had not tried his Fortune in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> nor could the Perſons ingaged aſſure his Return, even upon ſuch <hi>Condeſcenſions;</hi> yet the King granted under the Broad Seal of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, a full Redreſs for all Grievances, and that at the Requeſt of <hi>People</hi> that had oppoſed him; ſo that talking of Terms will be no harſh Language to him now; he can want no farther <hi>Illumination,</hi> by a longer Series of Misfortunes, to let him ſee, that Compliance with his People is his true and only Intereſt. In a private Pamphlet, and in a private Capacity,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:154028:4"/>it is not proper to ſtate the Manner and Bounds of our Redreſſes: But did ever People re-admit a King they had ejected upon the Male-admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of his Miniſters (if they could any ways help it) without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king good Proviſions? Can any body imagine we expect the People of <hi>England</hi> ſhould? The Men of S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſe, and Quality, and Eſtates, amongſt the <hi>Jacobites,</hi> be they <hi>Proteſtants</hi> or <hi>Papiſts,</hi> don't wiſh they ſhould do it. <hi>Would you have Tryals ſecured?</hi> It is the Intereſt of all Parties, care ſhould be taken about them, or all Parties will ſuffer in their turns. <hi>Plunket,</hi> and <hi>Sidney,</hi> and <hi>Aſhton,</hi> were doubtleſs all Murdered, tho they were never ſo guilty of the Crimes wherewith they were charged: The one Tryed twice, the other found guilty upon one Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and the laſt upon nothing but preſumptive Proof. Either let <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners</hi> have Counſel, or the <hi>Judges</hi> be forced to be more impartially ſo than they were in any of theſe Caſes; and let Juries underſtand that only <hi>Allegata</hi> and <hi>Probata</hi> are to direct their Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, and not <hi>Deadly Feuds, Foreign Belief, or State Neceſſity.</hi> In <hi>Scotland,</hi> at all <hi>Tryals,</hi> the whole is taken down in Writing, Word for Word, as well all Probations, as what is ſaid, both by the <hi>King's Advocate,</hi> and the <hi>Pannel</hi> or <hi>Criminal,</hi> and is all made a <hi>Record;</hi> that After-times (when the heat of the Proſecution is over) may examine whether the <hi>Judge</hi> dealt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially; and if he did not, and is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live at the review of thoſe <hi>Proceedings,</hi> if the Priſoner ſuffered <hi>Death</hi> by his <hi>warping the Law,</hi> the <hi>Judge</hi> is to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo the ſame <hi>Puniſhment;</hi> and if he is dead, the <hi>Heirs of the injur'd Perſon</hi> is to recover equal Damages to what they ſuſtained in their <hi>Fortune,</hi> by his <hi>illegal Sentence, from the Heirs of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt Judge.</hi> The <hi>Saxons</hi> puniſhed falſe <hi>Judges</hi> by giving Satisfaction <hi>to the Party wrong'd by them;</hi> and as the Caſe required, by <hi>Forfeiture of the Reſidue to the King, and by his diſabling them for ever for Places of Judicature,</hi> and by leaving their <hi>Lives</hi> to the <hi>King's Mercy.</hi> Who can have the Face to oppoſe the Revival of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing equivalent to that Law? But I will not diſcuſs too particularly the Particulars I ſhall mention. The granting of that <hi>Bill for Judges,</hi> that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> refuſed, and <hi>Whitlock's</hi> for <hi>Tryals,</hi> will be the Glory of King <hi>James</hi>'s Reign, whenever he is Reſtored.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>Armed Force</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> I think there may be ways found out to make our <hi>Militia</hi> as ſerviceable as any <hi>Mercenary Bands,</hi> to employ all our <hi>Officers</hi> that have had <hi>Military</hi> Experience, to raiſe from time to time ſuch Numbers of <hi>Officers,</hi> and ſuch Nurſeries of <hi>Private Centinels,</hi> as may make both the King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom <hi>ſafe,</hi> add to the <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> of our <hi>Monarch,</hi> and yet not leave the leaſt Umbrage for <hi>Jealouſie</hi> in the Minds of the <hi>People.</hi> But this is not a time of day for me to lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the World ſuch <hi>Plans.</hi> I will not hold forth ſuch Doctrines under any Government I think <hi>Unjuſt,</hi> and that I think too have not the <hi>Honeſty</hi> to embrace them if I would. But if ever I ſee an <hi>Engliſh Parliament</hi> under a <hi>Rightful</hi> Prince, I will not be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in offering my Mite, in this and all other things that may contribute to the Good of my Country: And ſure
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:154028:5"/>no body can be ſo unreaſonable as to be unwilling to hear from One that has given Teſtimony of his Loyalty to his <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Nation</hi> too, any thing that ſuch an One will propoſe, to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the <hi>Throne,</hi> and quiet the Minds of his Fellow-Subjects. <hi>Praetorian Bands</hi> in <hi>Rome</hi> Butchered as well as Guarded their <hi>Emperors.</hi> It is but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry lately that the <hi>Janiſaries</hi> Depoſed the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> and King <hi>James's own Army</hi> Deſerted from Him in theſe Kingdoms; and I am confident I can ſhew, that the Love of his Subjects is the beſt Standing Army for an <hi>Engliſh</hi> King as well as how he ſhall have it, and be able to look all his <hi>Foreign Enemies</hi> in the face to boot: But, I ſay, it is not time for the Publication of theſe things by my hand, nor will I be too prolix upon any one thing; therefore to come to <hi>Parliaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is there any Man of Senſe and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, that does not know them to be the <hi>Conſervators</hi> of all that we hold dear? Can there be an unjuſter thing, any thing more fatal, than a partial Repreſentation of the Minds and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of Men in that Houſe? Tho' this Reign has taught them to do ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little elſe but give <hi>Money,</hi> or <hi>Sanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to, or <hi>Pardons</hi> for the <hi>Irregularities of Miniſters;</hi> yet the Deſign of their Inſtitution is as well to provide <hi>Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> for the Complaints of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as <hi>Caſh</hi> for the Prince's Coffers. I will not debate what is neceſſary to make them <hi>Free,</hi> but I am ſure they ſhould be ſo. I will not ſay <hi>how often</hi> they muſt ſit, but I am ſure they ſhould <hi>frequently.</hi> Both theſe Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>teſt for their own Houſe, and I am not willing to make narrow Spirits peeviſh: But ſure no Man of Intereſt, or that hopes to keep any Reputation with the World, will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny they ſhould be <hi>free and frequent,</hi> and that they ſhould not be too much <hi>Officer'd,</hi> that they may be <hi>Faithful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not enter into a Detail of what is the <hi>Work</hi> of Parliaments; but there is One Thing I am ſure is very properly <hi>Theirs;</hi> and that is, to make an exact Scrutiny into the Publick Adminiſtration, and to bring Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters (who are above the reach of Common Courts of Judicature, and can ſtem all other Proſecutions;) I ſay, It is the Work of Parliaments to bring ſuch Miniſters to condign Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, if they deſerve it.</p>
            <p>I know not any thing wherein Princes, and ſome of their Subjects, have been more unfortunately miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, than in their Wiſhes that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters ſhould be <hi>Impunible:</hi> whereas <hi>Favourites that are not a Cement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween</hi> Prince <hi>and</hi> People, <hi>that don't conſult in all their Actions the Laws of the Conſtitution, and Inclinations of the Inhabitants, become Rocks of Offence, and bring Ruin, ſometimes upon</hi> Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>too often upon their</hi> Princes, <hi>and, God be praiſed for it, more generally upon</hi> Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. What is the Reaſon of that admirable Maxim, That <hi>the King of</hi> England <hi>can do wrong?</hi> Why do the People of <hi>England</hi> make him an <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curean</hi> God ſo happy in the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of His own Majeſty? Why do we ſay, That He neither can nor does diſturb the Peace of our World, but becauſe His Eyes and His Ears, His Omniſciency and His Omnipreſency, are comprehended in his Miniſters; but becauſe, if thoſe Miniſters are <hi>Troublers</hi> of our State, they are to be puniſhed, even for <hi>Inadvertencies,</hi> and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:154028:5"/>much more for <hi>Sins of Malice?</hi> Tho' this <hi>Revolution</hi> has blotted out all our <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Contract,</hi> razed all our Statutes and Law-Books, turned our Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy topſie-turvey, and ſcandalouſly prevaricated from all our Civil Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacts, by employing the Men that perſuaded King <hi>James</hi> to, and acted in what we imputed to him as falſe ſteps; yet it was his <hi>Miniſters</hi> ſhould have been puniſhed, and not he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf dethroned; and ſure King <hi>James,</hi> after he has found ſo many Miniſters were <hi>falſe,</hi> others <hi>flattering</hi> and <hi>fooliſh,</hi> cannot be unwilling to leave it an <hi>everlaſting Law</hi> to his and our Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that <hi>Miniſters ſhall be accountable.</hi> It is our <hi>Law,</hi> tho' both weak and profligate Men have, the one fancied, and the other pretended the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; and for that Reaſon, and that Reaſon only, it ought to be written more legibly in our Statute-Books: Is it not the Intereſt of Kings, that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters ſhould not <hi>Male-adminiſter</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all the Affection of their good and loving Subjects? Is it not the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of Kings, that the <hi>Repreſentative Body</hi> ſhould plainly ſhew them <hi>by whom</hi> and <hi>how</hi> they are betray'd? Yet, after all, thoſe that will read that excellent Chapter in <hi>Machiavel,</hi> which ſhews <hi>how neceſſary it is for the Conſervation of the State, that any Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen be ſecurely accuſed,</hi> p. 277. of his Works, ought to read the two next pages, which ſhew, that <hi>unjuſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies are no leſs pernicious to a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth than legal Accuſations are profitable and good;</hi> and there you will find a great difference betwixt <hi>Accuſation</hi> and <hi>Calumny. Miniſters</hi> ought to be puniſhed; I am ſatisfied the King is willing they ſhould be ſo, for the future: <hi>Sunderland's</hi> Miniſtry ſuggeſts that Advice to Him very ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually and ſtrongly; but <hi>Beaute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feaux</hi> alſo are to be ſuppreſſed in all well ordered States.</p>
            <p>One thing ſeems naturally here to fall in my way, which I beg leave to handle in the moſt inoffenſive manner that I can. I foreſee this will leſs pleaſe ſome Men, for whom no Man living can have a greater Honour than I have; yet I think it of ſo much Neceſſity and Importance, that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forbear mentioning it. There was not an ill thing done in King <hi>James</hi>'s Reign, that I did not call ſo then; and all that know me, know that I have taken it as my Province to repreſent Truths, be they never ſo bold or bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whilſt they are for Inſtruction. I I am no Advocate for any Man's Faults, nor for any Faults, tho' I would be charitable and good-natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, forgiving and forgetting, towards all Mens Perſons. Methinks the State of things require this meaſure. I ſcarce believe there ever was a Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od of Time, wherein an Univerſal Amneſty was ſo requiſite; a forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, as well as forgiveneſs of all paſt Crimes. Methinks all ſides ſtand in need of this Temper. If the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of King <hi>James</hi> exceeded in their Management of our Affairs, as doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they did, we have doubtleſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded too in our Revenge upon the King's Perſon; and beſides, thoſe that have fallen in with the Uſurpation have not proceeded againſt any one Man that has been in their hands, for any thing that was done amiſs in the two late Reigns; and therefore me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks it is very hard, if we cannot forgive <hi>thoſe</hi> that have undergone
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:154028:6"/>
               <hi>Baniſhment,</hi> (which in all Countries has been reckoned ſome ſort of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment) or ſuch as have hazarded <hi>Priſons,</hi> or the <hi>Gallows,</hi> every day. Why ſhould we not forgive all thoſe that ſerve him amongſt us, or that are with the <hi>King</hi> (tho' they may have had Faults) when we deſire, or I am ſure ought to deſire, that the whole Land ſhould be forgiven? All <hi>Parties,</hi> and <hi>almoſt all Men,</hi> have ſome way or other been to blame; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there ſeems to me to be a little too much <hi>Paſſion</hi> and <hi>Self-interest</hi> in keeping up <hi>old Grudges.</hi> I avoid ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is any infatuation in keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them up, tho' I cannot think that it is the likelieſt way to prepare the King to cloſe with Wiſe Councils, to revive or continue our Piques: For the King can ſcarce be ſuppoſed to be without ſome Kindneſs for thoſe who have either <hi>followed His Fortunes,</hi> or <hi>ventur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d their Necks for Him;</hi> and conſ quently, it is not perh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ps ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſable to make thoſe that tranſact in his Affairs (tho' they have been pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant) believe they can have no Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, no Share in him, unleſs he return with a High Hand. They will have ſome Opportunities to put ill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions upon good Advices. I have read of but few of thoſe Heroic Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits in any Age, who have ſo diveſted themſelves of all Regard for their own Perſons and Poſterity, as to be willing to become a Sacrifice to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. I think this Age affords feweſt Inſtances of thoſe Great Minds; and therefore I think it the likelieſt way to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke Men inſtrumental towards the Good of their Country, to ſhew them that they ſhall find their own Account in being ſo. I hope I have expreſſed my ſelf in as modeſt and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offenſive words as any, in which I could conceive my Thoughts; and I hope I ſhall not be ſo miſ-underſtood, as if I would juſtifie any thing that was by any body done amiſs; for I will not juſtifie a falſe ſtep, even in the <hi>King;</hi> but I would have us lay aſide all the Byaſſes of <hi>Factions</hi> and <hi>Friendſhips,</hi> and much more all <hi>Enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> that we may <hi>unanimouſly</hi> offer to the King Right Notions, and thereby <hi>Reſtore Him to His Hereditary Kingdoms.</hi> After all, I would not have leſs than ſuch a Repentance as gives evidence of <hi>Amendment</hi> entitle to <hi>Abſolution,</hi> but I would leave Room and Rewards for ſuch Repentance.</p>
            <p>I fear this Moderation, and <hi>forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of Enemies,</hi> will be thought a hard Leſſon; but, I bleſs God, I have practiſed it, and I think it not only the nobleſt Precept in <hi>Chriſtian Morality,</hi> but an admirable Rule in <hi>Civil Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> eſpecially in our Caſe; for it is as difficult for a Party that is ſubdivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded within it ſelf to pull down an <hi>Uſurpation,</hi> as it can be for a divided Kingdom to ſtand.</p>
            <p>But I am ſenſible I have made too long a Digreſſion, and therefore muſt omit many other particulars, upon which I would explain my ſelf, and the Senſe of many other <hi>Jacobites;</hi> and I can aſſure you, I am ſorry that any <hi>Jacobites</hi> ſay any thing that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends well-meaning Men: but I wiſh, for their own ſakes, my Country-men would not take a <hi>Standard,</hi> either of the <hi>King's Inclinations,</hi> or the reſt of his <hi>Friends,</hi> from their indiſcreet Tattle. There are in <hi>His Intereſt</hi> thoſe that know, that to talk too loftily and dogmatically, to diſpute, as they do
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:154028:6"/>in the Schools, concerning <hi>Prerogative</hi> and the Nature of <hi>Monarchy,</hi> to ſtand nicely upon Punctilio's, to conſult <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s and <hi>Xenophon</hi>'s Kings, is as unlikely a way to come to a mutual Accommodation, as to peruſe and and or am of <hi>Plato's Commonwealth,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas More's Utop a, Harrington's Oceana,</hi> &amp;c. There are Men of his ſid, that think (as the great Lawgiver <hi>Solon</hi> did) that a Government muſt be framed according to the Nature of the Governed, and that he is the beſt <hi>Subject,</hi> as well as <hi>Politician,</hi> that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dapts all his Notions to our Tempers; that conſiders <hi>Men,</hi> as well as peruſes <hi>Books,</hi> when he is to draw a Scheme; and I believe, as you ſay, that the high flights of ſome <hi>Jacobites</hi> hinder many honeſt Men from coming into his Intereſt; and farther, that they ſometimes miſlead the King. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, there are in his Intereſt Men that I aſſure you are not <hi>frighted at Words,</hi> nor <hi>ſtartled at Nicknames,</hi> that know the King of <hi>England</hi> makes the greateſt Figure in <hi>Europe</hi> when he is beſt with his People, and that is when he governs by the Meaſures of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monweal. Theſe Men know, <hi>a good Commonwealths-man</hi> was not a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of Reproach in our Legiſlation and Politicks, till all our Glory dwin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled, and the <hi>Abſoluteneſs</hi> of <hi>Miniſters</hi> was more conſulted than the <hi>true In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> of <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Kingdom;</hi> till a pack of Knaves forged a <hi>ſeparate Intereſt</hi> between the King of <hi>England</hi> and his People, and till they began to call a Mix'd Monarchy an <hi>errant Bull,</hi> and would Reform our State by Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſical and Court Diſtinctions: whereas, if our Hiſtories and Statute-Books were conſulted, they are every where full of Explanations. Are theſe Gentlemen you complain of weary of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> (which was but a Revival and Recitation of the <hi>Saxon Liberties,</hi> and ancient <hi>Britiſh Laws?</hi>) I will prove them farther, That <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Lawful Prerogatives</hi> may be ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed, that it may be fit to take away the One, and to deſire that the Other may never be again ſo uſed; and that our former Kings have thought ſo. But I will go no farther back than the Conjunction of the <hi>Two Roſes,</hi> and they may find that in <hi>Henry</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth's Time <hi>Empſon</hi> and <hi>Dudley</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſſed the People by obſolete unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed Laws; nay, it has never been thought <hi>mean</hi> by our greateſt Kings to make <hi>Condeſcentions</hi> to their People: And, as haughty as King <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. was, my Lord <hi>Herbert</hi> in his Hiſtory of his Reign, tells you, That in his firſt Parliament he Repealed, Explained, or Limited thoſe Statutes, by which his Father had taken Advantage of his People; and (as my Lord <hi>Herbert</hi> judiciouſly obſerves therein) <hi>was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to reſtrain his own Authority, in ſome ſort, that he might enlarge the Peoples Confidence and Affection.</hi> This that King did in the celebrated part, to wit, in the beginning of his Reign, tho' he had at the ſame time his Exchequer what was equivalent to Seven Millions Sterling now, and was in peaceable Poſſeſſion of his Throne, and had no particular preſſing Occaſion to pleaſe his People. How much more neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is this meaſure to regain the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Confidence and Affection towards an <hi>Exil'd Prince?</hi> The Author of this Hiſtory (my Lord <hi>Herbert</hi> of <hi>Cherbury</hi>) profeſſes in his Epiſtle Dedicatory great Deſerence to Kings; and that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:154028:7"/>the King (to whom he dedicates his Hiſtory) <hi>had luſtrated by his Gracious Eye, and conſummated by his Judicious Animadverſions, all the parts of that Hiſtory, as faſt as he finiſhed them.</hi> And therefore this Inſtance ought to be of great weight with every body, even with thoſe <hi>Jacobites</hi> you talk of. <hi>It is a Royal, as well as my Lord</hi> Herbert's Hiſtory <hi>of</hi> Henry <hi>VIII.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am not ignorant, that this King <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. is brought as an Inſtance of a King that could pull up Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, and do what he pleaſed; but there was a ſtrange Concurrence in his Time to help him in the buſineſs he was doing, and he did it by <hi>Parliaments,</hi> and often uſed Palliations; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps if a Man looks obſervingly upon his Life, he was but the Head of the Rabble-rout; and that neither He nor the People knew what he would be at. It was an Age big with Changes; and his greateſt Exorbitances fell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſort of People who were wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into diſeſteem, or were of a more private Nature. Beſides, he began his Reign with a wondrous good Grace, and he ſacrific'd now and then a <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter;</hi> and what he took from the <hi>Church,</hi> he divided amongſt the <hi>Gentry</hi> and <hi>Nobility.</hi> But, after all, I will own there are ſome Periods of his Reign, wherein the <hi>Prince</hi> went farther and faſter than the <hi>Peeple,</hi> and he had the good luck to do ſtrange things by in comprehenſible ways: For my Lord <hi>Herbert</hi> of <hi>Cherbury</hi> (as judicious and ſharp-ſighted an Author as he is) ſeems to wonder, and not to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand all the Occurrences of his Reign. His beginning it ſo condeſcendingly, makes it leſs a wonder, that the People were a great while apt to put good Conſtructions upon what he did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. He gave up <hi>Empſon</hi> and <hi>Dudley</hi> meerly to their Rage; and <hi>Woolſey</hi>'s Fall was pleaſing; and, as I juſt now intimated, he was more Sacrilegious towards the Church, which was then going down with the People, than he was otherwiſe Oppreſſive.</p>
            <p>The next Perſon I will introduce ſhall be Qu. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> whoſe Speech in the 43d year of her Reign, occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by Complaints againſt Monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, is ſo excellent, that I think fit to tranſcribe it at length; tho' I will not commend the <hi>Sanguinary Laws</hi> ſhe made in matters of Religion, as well againſt <hi>Browniſts,</hi> &amp;c. as <hi>Papiſts,</hi> no more than I will many other parts of her Reign. I have often wondred why <hi>meer Church of England-men</hi> cried out againſt, or <hi>Whigs</hi> ſo much extoll'd her, ten or twelve years ago; for ſhe was a <hi>meer Church of England-Queen:</hi> but I proteſt I know not how enough to commend this Speech which ſhe made to her Parliament; I wiſh eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry body would peruſe the Context of it in <hi>Camden,</hi> but the words of it are theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <q>We owe unto you ſpecial Thanks and Commendations for your ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Good will towards us, not in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Thought, but in plain Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion expreſſed; whereby ye have called us back from an Error, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from ignorance, not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſs. Theſe things had undeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly turned to our diſgrace (to whom nothing is more dear than the Safety and Love of our People) had not ſuch Harpies and Horſe-leeches as theſe been made known unto us by you. I had rather be maimed in
<pb facs="tcp:154028:7"/>Hand to give allowance of ſuch Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges of Monopolies as may be prejudicial to my People. The Brightneſs of Regal Majeſty hath not ſo blinded mine Eyes, that licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Power ſhould prevail more with me, than Juſtice. The Glory of the Name of a King may deceive unskilful Princes, as guilded Pills may deceive a ſick Patient, but I am none of thoſe Princes; for I know that the Commonwealth is to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned for the benefit of thoſe who are committed, not of thoſe to whom it is committed; and that an Account is one day to be given before another Judgment-Seat. I think my ſelf moſt happy, that by God's aſſiſtance I have hitherto ſo governed the whole Commonwealth, and have ſuch Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, as for their Good I would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly leave both Kingdom and Life alſo. I beſeech you that what Faults others have committed by falſe Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions, may not be imputed to me. Let the Teſtimony of a clear Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience be my abſolute Excuſe. Ye are not ignorant that Princes Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants are now and then too attentive to their own benefit, that the Truth is often concealed from Princes; and they cannot themſelves look preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into all things, upon whoſe Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders lieth continually the Weight of the greateſt Buſineſs.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot but obſerve, before I go any farther, that this Queen was not willing to take upon her ſelf the faults of her Servants; but, on the contrary, gave them very hard Names. I muſt obſerve likewiſe, that <hi>Commonwealth</hi> was no odious Word then; for ſhe twice in this Speech; and in her time Secretary <hi>Smith</hi> wrote a Book of our Government, to which he gave that Title. This was an Age wherein <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> could court, and <hi>Miniſters</hi> affect to be Patriots of the People; and yet <hi>Prerogative</hi> did not loſe much ground, altho' it ſometimes yielded.</p>
            <p>But I will come nearer to our Times, as far as the Union of this <hi>Iſland.</hi> Sir <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> adviſed King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt (as you may find in his <hi>Reſuſcitatio</hi>) to amend by conſent of Parliament ſome of our Laws, and to expunge others, eſpecially Penal Ones.</p>
            <p>He quotes <hi>a Learned Civilian</hi> (tho' he does not name him) <hi>that expoundeth the Curſe of the Prophet,</hi> Plu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſuper eos L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>queos, <hi>of multitude of Penal Laws; which</hi> (continues he) <hi>are worſe than Showrs of Hail, or Tempeſts upon Cattel; for they fall upon Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He goes on, <hi>There are ſome Penal Laws fit to be retained, but the Penalty too great. And it is ever a Rule, That any over-great Penalty (beſide the acer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bity of it) deads the Execution of the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſays alſo, <hi>There is a farth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience of Penal Laws obſolete and out of uſe; for it brings a gangrene neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, and habit diſobedience upon other wholſom Laws, that are fit to be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in practice and execution. So that our Laws endure the Torment of</hi> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>zen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, The Living die in the Arms of the Dead.</p>
            <p>I choſe to expreſs my Lord <hi>Bac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi>'s Mind in his own Words: But I will add to what he has ſaid a farther in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience that I my ſelf have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in the reading of Hiſtories;
<pb facs="tcp:154028:8"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Powers,</hi> and <hi>ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olete Penal Laws,</hi> have not only proved a Snare to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but given Kings too often an Handle to fall into ſuch Meaſures as have proved deſtructive to themſelves. <hi>Powers in a Crown, that are wholly unfit to be exerciſed, are only Temptations to Oppreſſion and Miſunderstanding. Knight Service</hi> was once a very Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Tenure: It was once fit, before the ſeveral People of this Kingdom were mixed and civiliſed, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever was born upon a <hi>Lord</hi>'s Land, ſhould be brought up under <hi>his</hi> Care; and that no Woman that held Land of any Lord ſhould carry her Eſtate to any Man that was an Enemy to that Lord: yet in King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt's days, the ſame Sir <hi>Francis Bacon,</hi> tho' then Sollicitor-General to him, in a Conference with the Lords, by Commiſſion from the Commons, made a Speech to perſuade the Lords to joyn with the Commons in a Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the King, to obtain Liberty to treat of a Compoſition with his Majeſty for <hi>Wards</hi> and <hi>Tenures</hi> This was in the ſeventh year of K. <hi>James</hi>'s Reign, in <hi>Halcyon</hi>-days. The Speech is in the 34th page of my Lord <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con</hi>'s <hi>Reſuſcitatio,</hi> and worth any Man's reading. He therein propoſeth, in Recompence of the Revenue of Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nures, a more ample, a more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and a more <hi>Loving Dowry; Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Dowry</hi> expreſſeth admirably well, that Kings ſhould be willing to change any part of their Revenue, for what may ſuit better with the Peoples inclinations. But I won't make Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks upon this Speech.</p>
            <p>The next Paragraph ſpeaks of the Nature of thoſe things, and how it is changed with the times. <hi>Voca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> manent, Res fugiunt,</hi> are his words.</p>
            <p>And the next Paragraph to that ſays a great deal in theſe two Axioms, <hi>Naturae vis maxima, &amp; ſuus cuique diſcretus ſanguis:</hi> for reſtoring Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to the care of their moſt affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate Relatives.</p>
            <p>I come to the Reign of K. <hi>Charles</hi> I<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and muſt ſay, that the ſtrained uſe of ſome Powers and Prerogatives, for which the flattering Lawyers had ſome dark ſemblance of Authority in our Law-Books, gave the fatal Riſe to the late <hi>Civil Wars,</hi> which ended in the horrid Murther of that King; and when K. <hi>Charles</hi> II. was Reſtored, tho' the firſt Parliament he called will be allowed by every body to be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently devoted to him, yet he therein, when they were under the greateſt Tranſports and Raptures of Loyalty, paſſed many Acts that plainly own the <hi>great Inexpediency,</hi> if not <hi>Illegality</hi> of ſeveral things done in his Father's Days, and ſecured us againſt the like Abuſes hereafter; and had he lived, he muſt have owned that he himſelf had carried the <hi>Quo Warrantoes</hi> too far, or he would have ſate uneaſie; and thoſe very Men that were inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental in <hi>Quo-Warrantoing Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> did every where declare, that <hi>Regulations,</hi> which (however illegal I take them to be in themſelves, how much ſoever I think them a <hi>Fanatick Rowland</hi> for the <hi>Church of England Oliver,</hi> yet I think they were agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Powers the Crown reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to its ſelf in the <hi>New Charters;</hi>) I ſay, That thoſe very Men that were inſtrumental to the <hi>Quo Warrantoing Corporations,</hi> did every where declare, that the <hi>Regulations</hi> in the ſucceeding
<pb facs="tcp:154028:8"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Power</hi> inſecure, and reſolved all our Government into an <hi>Abſolute</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotick Rule.</hi> Queſtionleſs there ſhould be ſome way to puniſh the <hi>Abuſes</hi> in Corporations, but the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> that are againſt <hi>Corporations</hi> have perhaps annexed to them <hi>too great a Penalty;</hi> perhaps it would be better to puniſh the <hi>Perſons</hi> that offend, than to fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the poor <hi>innocent Charter. I would have the Body Corporate be able to do no wrong, tho' the Members may.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is not my buſineſs in this place to propound the <hi>Remedies,</hi> but to ſhew that it is lawful to make, and that there uſed to be made, and that there ought to be <hi>Reformations</hi> now, as well as there have been formerly. And I hope I have made it plain, both from our <hi>Hiſtories</hi> and <hi>Statute-Books,</hi> That <hi>Civil Infallibility</hi> was not former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an <hi>Article in our Politicks,</hi> nor has it the <hi>Univerſality</hi> on its ſide; nor will any Party abide by it, unleſs for Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Ends, or when it ſerves their own Party. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it in their days; the Church of <hi>England</hi> did not believe it when His Majeſty was amongſt us; and the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticks</hi> never pretended to believe it. Thus you ſee my thoughts; and, as different as they may be from the <hi>Williamites</hi> that have deluded, or from the <hi>Jacobites</hi> that have afrighted you, I defie any of the One to be readier to hazard themſelves for their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, or the Other to venture farther for the Service of King <hi>James.</hi> All that I deſire is, That the King may have for his Motto what the ſincere Hiſtorian ſays of the two beſt Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of <hi>Rome. Tacitus</hi> his words are, DIVUS NERVA, ET DIVUS TRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> MISCUERUNT, IMPERIUM ET LIBERTATEM. And may the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of King <hi>James</hi> the Second's days give yet leave, after He has lived long here, to write upon his Tomb, <hi>Divus</hi> JACOBUS <hi>Secundus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Res olim inſociabiles miſcuit Imperium &amp; Libertatem.</hi> I would have the <hi>King</hi> conſult his own Honour; but I think he does it beſt, when he conſiders well and throughly of the Liberties of the People. I allow that Maxim to be true, <hi>Principum actiones proecipue ſunt ad famam componendoe.</hi> But no <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh King</hi> will preſerve his Memory grateful, in the <hi>Records</hi> of <hi>Time,</hi> or his Name dreadful in <hi>Foreign Courts,</hi> who is not beloved by his People; and none will be ſo, that does not care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Fence, and inviolably preſerve our Rights. We have been a People always jealous of our Rights, <hi>Tena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſimi libertatis.</hi> The Word <hi>Conqueſt</hi> is often met with in our common Hiſtories, and miſleads our common Readers; but though our Nation has been often ſtormed, our <hi>Eſſential Laws</hi> and <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> were never carried. The <hi>Romans</hi> governed us, in great part, by our own Laws, and the wiſeſt of their Lieutenants found we were more eaſily governed by <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>Juſtice,</hi> than by <hi>Force.</hi> The <hi>Danes</hi> made no alteration in our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution; and the <hi>Saxon</hi> and <hi>Norman</hi> Invaſions ended in Treaty; and the <hi>Saxon</hi> Government was <hi>homogeneous</hi> to our Temperament; and when <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> (called the <hi>Conqueror</hi>) would have introduced the <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> the People neither would, nor did receive them. If a Man reads Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories to underſtand Government, he
<pb facs="tcp:154028:9"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Tale</hi> of them; and whoever looks in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our Antiquities, will find the foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of our Liberties are as ancient as of our Being. But to return to what I was ſaying ſome time ſince, I would not injure my Country for K. <hi>James,</hi> nor would I injure K. <hi>James</hi> for my Country. I think your Party wicked, and I fear too many <hi>Jaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites</hi> are weak: They are weak by <hi>fantaſtick Notions,</hi> and <hi>violent Aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> and <hi>Perſonal, Party,</hi> and <hi>Church-Quarrels.</hi> But I would rather lament, than expoſtulate too freely, and I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire no body to ſerve King <hi>James,</hi> but on the Principles of making him the <hi>Father</hi> of his Country: I once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain aſſure you, I neither do, nor will upon any other; and were he rein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtated in his Throne, if he purſued partial Notions, and ungrateful Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, I would rather make a Vow of Voluntary Exile, than accept the beſt Employment that a King of <hi>England</hi> has in his Power to give: I have many times told Him ſo. And farther, I would always adviſe him to take into his Buſineſs Popular Men, and to let them ſerve him by the Methods that made them Popular: But at the ſame time, I ſay, I would adviſe him to <hi>forget</hi> as well as <hi>forgive</hi> all our Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages. I would have a <hi>perfect Act of Oblivion</hi> from Him; and I would have the People paſs on their part ſo entire an <hi>Act of Oblivion,</hi> that they ſhould not gall any one Man for what they did amiſs in his <hi>Reign,</hi> or under this <hi>Uſurpation,</hi> on condition they te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie their Repentance by their Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Life. Tho' <hi>Henry</hi> 4. of <hi>France</hi> (ſo juſtly called the <hi>Great</hi>) was in his abſence arraigned and condemned to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Harquebuſſes; and this by the Votes and Order of the Parliament of <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſe;</hi> yet, notwithſtanding he reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered his Kingdom by force of Arms, that Great and Excellent King did not in the leaſt revenge their Trayterous and Rebellious Uſage; by which Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous as well as Politick Carriage, he added to the Conqueſt of his Country the Conqueſt of the Hearts of all his People, reconciling at once all the Animoſities and Factions which had been the Product of near Forty Years Civil Wars. Let a new Face of things ariſe likewiſe out of our State-Chaos. May the King govern with that Equal Hand, that <hi>Merit</hi> may be rewarded, and nothing but <hi>Vice</hi> in diſgrace; that thoſe may be thought to ſerve him beſt, that moſt ſerve the General Good; and let it be a <hi>Crime,</hi> as well as <hi>ill Manners,</hi> to revive any of our old Diſtinctions; let there be no diſtinction upon the account of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> or <hi>Civil Faith;</hi> and let <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Allegiance</hi> to the <hi>Civil Power</hi> be the only <hi>Teſt</hi> for Preferment. You know, my Friend! I am no <hi>Papiſt,</hi> tho' I am for a Civil Comprehenſion: And as falſly as your <hi>Iriſh</hi> Dr. <hi>King</hi> has traduc'd His Majeſty for what he did in <hi>Ireland,</hi> I am told one thing for which his Wiſdom and Goodneſs can never be enough commended; and that is, that he required no <hi>Oath</hi> from any one Man that ſerv'd him, but truſted to their <hi>Honour</hi> and their <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt,</hi> rather than the <hi>Obligation of Oaths,</hi> being ſure an honeſt Man would do his Duty without them; and being alſo convinced by a <hi>late</hi> and <hi>ſad Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience,</hi> that they never bind a Knave. And thus he truly made himſelf the King of all Perſwaſions.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:154028:9"/>
            <p>The Diſcipline of the <hi>Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuns</hi> was poſitive, That every Man ſhould keep his <hi>Rank or Die;</hi> yet they never put an Oath to their Souldiers: <hi>Shame</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> had more Power over thoſe brave Minds, made them even ſcorn Death (which is the greateſt Tryal) had a more infallible effect upon them, than we can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend all Oaths have upon us.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding this ſhort Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark about Oaths, I am neither <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> nor <hi>Sectaria;</hi> therefore a hint is enough from me upon that Subject: But from the ſeveral Heads of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe I have handled, methinks I find my ſelf under a neceſſity of clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, at leaſt, briefly Three things, and I will do it as briefly as I can.</p>
            <p>The Firſt is, That thoſe that are both <hi>Zealous</hi> and <hi>Jealous</hi> for <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property</hi> are more in number, than thoſe that are for the <hi>Strains</hi> and <hi>Stretches</hi> of Prerogative.</p>
            <p>I find there is a vaſt and unlucky miſtake in the Computations of ſome People, and that by reaſon that they do not diſtinguiſh between the <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Religious Whigg.</hi> I allow the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natick Whigg,</hi> or thoſe that refuſe to come to our Communion, are not perhaps the <hi>twentieth Man</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> but there are very great numbers of Men, who never went formerly, nor do now go, even by reaſon of their Principle, to any other <hi>Church</hi> but the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> There are likewiſe many others, who are not at all Biggotted to any particular Form of <hi>Church Worſhip,</hi> who yet moſtly, if not altogether, go to the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and yet both the one and the other of theſe are as much, or perhaps more nicely <hi>Whiggs</hi> in <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils,</hi> than are the <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> though not ſo generally called ſo: So that there are Church of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudinarian,</hi> or (as the <hi>Scotch</hi> call them) <hi>Eraſtian</hi> as well as <hi>Fanatick Whiggs.</hi> Now let us conſider what Intereſt all theſe Three ſort of <hi>Whiggs</hi> have in our Affairs; what influence they have over them; and you will find by Matter of Fact, that theſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years laſt paſt, they all joyning up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a <hi>Civil Bottom,</hi> have all along been too hard for that which is the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as it is <hi>contra diſtinguiſhed</hi> to the <hi>Whigg.</hi> They were fatally ſo in King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt's Time. But to bring things within all our Memories and Obſervation, the three laſt Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments in King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's Reign, is not an improper Seaſon to calculate their Intereſt and Influence: For then they choſe before any illegal or unwarrantable Tricks had been plaid by either ſide with <hi>Charters,</hi> and if the Nation was inflamed by a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Plot, I am ſure the Court lean'd wholly to the High Prerogative Church of <hi>England.</hi> Then you ſee that the <hi>Bill of Excluſion</hi> (tho' it was an exceſſive and exotick Rant, rather than a natural Effect or Production of <hi>Whiggiſm</hi>) was carried in the Houſe of Commons, and that tho' almoſt all the Members were <hi>Charch goers</hi> But I will ſhew you yet by a later Inſtance, that <hi>State Whiggiſm</hi> runs thro this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. All thoſe that are for this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment act upon that Principle, and lay aſide the <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> and <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative Notions</hi> of the high Church of <hi>England</hi> men; notwithſtanding that they keep up the <hi>Epiſcopal Order,</hi> the <hi>Pomp, Ceremony,</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> And whoever
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:154028:10"/>will turn one a King for <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le-admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration</hi> of his <hi>Miniſters,</hi> will never receive him without a <hi>Reformation</hi> in the <hi>Conſtitution:</hi> They will be <hi>State-Whigs,</hi> tho' they do not call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo. It is for <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty</hi> that theſe Men ſtruggle, tho' they do not know how to name their own Actions.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing that ſeems neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for me to clear, is, That it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to give a <hi>Liberty of Conſcience;</hi> and that theſe Aſſertors of <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property</hi> will be for Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and be able, upon the King's giving good Securities for our Civil Rights, to give in exchange of them an Impartial Toleration. I will not diſpute the inconſiſtency of Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with either the Chriſtian or Moral Law; nor will I take pains to prove that where a Nation is greatly divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into Sects, it is the Intereſt of that Nation to give every body leave to worſhip God in their own manner: but I will ſhew the likelihood that the <hi>State-Whigs</hi> ſhould and will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change <hi>Religi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us Liberty</hi> for <hi>Civil Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity.</hi> And now I muſt again carry you back to the beginning of the late Civil Wars, and then you will find, becauſe the Church of <hi>England</hi> would not give Liberty of Conſcience, the State-Whigs ſet up <hi>Presbytery.</hi> The next Conſultation, I muſt make you acquainted with, are the Debates of the above-mentioned three laſt Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, and you may eaſily recollect they were for Liberty of Conſcience to all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Diſſenters; nay, they made ſome Votes that were thought extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant in their favour, ſome <hi>ſuſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſpenſing Votes;</hi> for they reſolved it as the Opinion of that Houſe, that it was contrary to the Intereſt of the Nation, to put the Laws (which were then in being) in execution againſt them: But you will ſay they did not Vote as much for the <hi>Papiſts.</hi> You muſt conſider the Seaſon. Beſides that, the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have been eſteemed errant <hi>Courtiers</hi> ever ſince the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</hi> The Pacliament then thought they had a Popiſh Plot on foot; they thought that Plot was not a Plot for Liberty to worſhip in the Popiſh Way, but to introduce Popery, by the Deſtruction of all our Civil and Religious Liberties. You know at the beginning of my Letter I charged my Country with <hi>National Intoxications:</hi> We can at ſome times believe <hi>Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Pilgrims, Black Bills,</hi> St. <hi>Jones</hi>'s <hi>Gridirons,</hi> and that <hi>three thouſand Iriſh</hi> can <hi>Maſſacre</hi> all <hi>England.</hi> And when that Popiſh Plot was proſecuted ſo violently, the generality of Men looked upon the <hi>Papiſts</hi> as <hi>Banditti</hi> and <hi>Miſanthropi,</hi> in relation to the <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> they looked upon them as the <hi>Partizans</hi> or <hi>Janizaries</hi> of the <hi>Court,</hi> Propagators of Civil as well as Religious Superſtition and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. And if theſe Men had a mind to ruin the Papiſts at that day, it was not becauſe of their Prayers and Beads, but becauſe they thought them Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to our Conſtitution; not only from their dependance upon the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man See;</hi> but for a miſchief that was nigher at hand, their exceſſive flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the <hi>Court</hi> and <hi>Crown;</hi> whereas the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> being avowedly tender of <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property,</hi> were not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly favoured by all thoſe Parliaments, but influenced great numbers of thoſe who were not of their own Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:154028:10"/>at the reſpective Elections of each of thoſe Parliaments: So that the Principle of <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> was perfectly prevalent, though they held a ſtrict hand over the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> out of the Principle of Self-preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; and conſequently, a truly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choſen Parliament will make the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men where they find them ſo. In farther proof of this laſt Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, I muſt beg you to remember how <hi>King James's Declaration of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence</hi> was at firſt entertained. I know the Univerſal Joy with which it was firſt received laſted but a little while; but I know that tho' the <hi>Whigs</hi> miſliked that it ſhould be put out upon a <hi>Diſpenſing Power;</hi> yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving it a Preface to Comprehenſive Meaſures and Latitudinarian Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, they forgave that blemiſh in its Birth; and every where ſo unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly embraced it, that thoſe nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Spirits of the Church of <hi>England</hi> who had a mind, were aſhamed, if not afraid to oppoſe it. <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> would have made K. <hi>James</hi> the Second Memorable and Glorious in our Hiſtories, had not <hi>Sunderland</hi>'s Artifices, ſuch Speeches as Mr. <hi>Alſop</hi>'s, and ſuch Pampalets as <hi>Can there come any Good out of Galilee?</hi> ſpoil'd the Nobleſt Project any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Monarch ever ſet on foot, which was, <hi>A ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Religious from Civil Intereſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſs we can make Popery a Ball-begger when we pleaſe, and that ought to teach the Papiſts Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; bue the <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property</hi>-men can alſo call off the <hi>Mob</hi> when they pleaſe: For you ſee at this time the Nation finds no fault with the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror's and the Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi>'s Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry and Perſecution; no nor with the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Inquiſition, whilſt they fancy (tho' wildly and falſly) they are by their help ſupporting their own Civil Rights. They fall not upon the Papiſts here, that they may not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe the Confederates abroad; ſo that Popery is not ſo dreadful, as Property and Privileges are dear and charming.</p>
            <p>And now ſince I have been proving that Intereſt governs the World, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Men may miſtake what is their own Intereſt, I think my ſelf obliged in the third place to ſhew that it is the Intereſt of the King, and every ſort of Men, that he ſhould be Reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon Civil Securities; and that it is not the Intereſt of the King, or any ſort of Men, to endeavour that the <hi>Reſtauration</hi> ſhould be put upon any other Foot.</p>
            <p>Whilſt I ſhew that it is the <hi>King's Intereſt,</hi> I ſhall anſwer the Objection of thoſe who ſay the <hi>Whigs</hi> won't think their Properties and Privileges ſufficiently ſecured, unleſs the King part with ſome of his Prerogative. I am ſure whilſt he is <hi>diſpoſſeſſed</hi> he has <hi>no Prerogative,</hi> or at leaſt no exerciſe of, and benefit by it; and the Chance of War is too doubtful to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſhall have any, unleſs the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple pleaſe. He is <hi>outed</hi> of his Eſtate, and can in all probability only have it upon Compoſition; which if he will not make with us, the Nation will try to the laſt to keep the Poſſeſſion; and it has thoſe <hi>eleven points of the Law.</hi> Nor are all things Prerogatives that flattering Lawyers have called ſo in <hi>Weſtminſter Hall,</hi> and ſome well-meaning, and other ſelf-deſigning, Ciergy-men, have believed ſo in their Cloſets, or preached for as ſuch in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:154028:11"/>their Pulpits. They can ſee farther than I, that expect to do any thing without an <hi>Accommodation.</hi> I think it impoſſible he ſhould be <hi>Reſtored,</hi> or were he, that he ſhould <hi>keep</hi> his <hi>Throne,</hi> without it. I think it impoſſible for One Man to govern the People of <hi>England,</hi> unleſs they have a mind he ſhould; and they will never have ſuch a mind, unleſs he ſometimes gives way to their Impetuoſities. But farther, <hi>His Age,</hi> and the <hi>Minority</hi> of his <hi>Son,</hi> are the higheſt Inducements imaginable for him to endeavour to leave a ſettled Government, to <hi>quiet the Minds, as well as ſuppreſs the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections of the People.</hi> There is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe another Reaſon, why as a Man of Conſcience he muſt be yielding; for be cannot but be willing that his <hi>Son</hi> ſhould be educated in his own <hi>Religion;</hi> and if he will let the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> be ſecure of their own <hi>Religion,</hi> and of their own <hi>Laws,</hi> notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that the <hi>Crown</hi> ſhould be of <hi>one</hi> Religion, and the <hi>People</hi> of <hi>another,</hi> I am ſatisfied that the People of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> will be little ſollicitous <hi>which way</hi> our Kings think the <hi>beſt</hi> to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. This has Argument, as he is a Religious Man. But I muſt again in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force Condeſcentions, as the Intereſt of the King under a Natural Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. <hi>Good Securities</hi> will make the Nation own the <hi>Legitimacy</hi> of his <hi>Son</hi> more than all other <hi>Proofs;</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out out good Securities, there will be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences that his Birth is diſputable; (though I affirm it impoſſible for any thinking Man to queſtion in his own Mind the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi>'s being born of the Queen's Body.) Compliance with the People made Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi>'s Title unqueſtioned; ſo that thoſe that flatter the King with <hi>His Right,</hi> and ſeem to deſpiſe <hi>our Rights,</hi> take the moſt infallible Courſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy both the King and his Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>I need not have ſaid one Word of this matter to inform the King's Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for he is in that Temper in which his Subjects wiſh him, and that would ſatisfie a <hi>Parliament-Houſe,</hi> were he to receive their Petitions and Addreſſes, to ſtamp their Votes, and to end our Diſputes. I do not ſpeak this by gueſs, but am convinced of it by many Diſcourſes I have had the Honour perſonally to have with him, ſince his Misfortunes; and the Letters I have had from ſeveral of the beſt hands ſince I left his Court, confirm me he remains in the ſame Opinion. But I thought it was neceſſary to ſay ſomething of this ſort, to ſet before thoſe <hi>Jacobites</hi> you complain of, the <hi>Interest</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> in the trueſt light.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Whiggs</hi> of all ſorts, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Body knows that they will find their Account in a <hi>Reſtauration</hi> upon Civil Securities, and that no other Reſtauration will pleaſe them: So that I will not labour that matter at all; but haſten to ſhew that it is the Intereſt both of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Catholicks</hi> to promote ſuch a <hi>Reſtauration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> is not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure that ſhe ſhall be continued the <hi>National Church,</hi> ſo long as there is unlimmited and unexplained Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Power; and ſhe ſaw <hi>Quo War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranto</hi>'s could produce Regulations, and ſo I might go through other
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:154028:11"/>things. And the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick King may again miſtake in the Exerciſe of his Power, if the Boundaries of the Adminiſtration are not plainly chalk'd out; and whilſt the Church of <hi>England</hi> appear Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property,</hi> they will loſe their Intereſt with the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and the next Revolution will conclude in <hi>Presbytery</hi> and a <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth:</hi> For Popery wants Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to eſtabliſh its ſelf; though ſome of the Members of that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion may have Vanity enough to hope to eſtabliſh it; and if the Church of <hi>England</hi> do not joyn in Civil Seourities; nay, if there ſhould be a Reſtauration without them, thoſe Catholicks (though it will be to their certain Ruine) may be able to do enough towards it, to make the Church of <hi>England</hi> fall, and the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> get all in the Scramble. And tho' the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> have an odd han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kering after a King; yet, after they have been bit once more, they will become tuneable to a <hi>Democracy. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can deſtroy the Church of</hi> England, <hi>but their Oppoſition to the Liberties of their</hi> Country, <hi>or to</hi> Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, <hi>or their cloſing with</hi> Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion.</p>
            <p>It is a little light, but however I will ſet down what I have often heard ſaid concerning it by Men of very large Minds. They have ſaid, That if the Members of the Church of <hi>England</hi> were as good-natur'd as the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>it is the beſt-bred, civileſt National Church in Chriſtendom.</hi> I ſet it down as a light expreſſion to be uſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Church-Affairs, and yet there may be Inſtruction in it: For I believe its Civility, if it does not make too <hi>extravagant Compliments</hi> of our <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> will for ever make it ſtand; but if our <hi>Liberties</hi> are not well guarded, that may be pulled down, and <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery</hi> will be ſet up.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> I think it is in the higheſt degree improbable that the King ſhould ever be able to come home by <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> and yet more improbable he ſhould be able to ſtay here upon that <hi>Title,</hi> (if in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is One in a Natural King:) and if the Catholicks would in all places declare for Civil Securities, I think this is the propereſt Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity for their Incorporation Our having been in Confederacy with Princes of that Perſwaſion, has made us capable of allowing fair Quarter to thoſe Catholicks that are here. We can follow our Intereſt, notwithſtanding our old Grudges, and if the Catholicks will come to a Temper, we are enough in one to embody them: Whereas, ſhould not the Reſtauration be in the Life of the King, the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> would be fetched home upon a <hi>meer Church of England Plot,</hi> and the Proofs of his Birth will be Authentick, and without diſpute, during his Non-age, and till he has diſobliged us; and the <hi>Church of England men</hi> will, in point of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, carry all things before them, as far as is in Oppoſition to Popery; he will be bred up a Proteſtant, and muſt, in Proof of his being ſo, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to any farther Laws that the Church of <hi>England</hi> will think neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to ſecure their Church againſt Popery: So far will it then be from repealing the Teſt, or even the Penal
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:154028:12"/>Laws, in relation to Catholicks. And the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> whilſt they may have their <hi>Church</hi> ſecured, will, during the Minority of the Prince, (before <hi>Flattery</hi> will advance to <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment</hi>) agree with the <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property</hi> men for any good and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Laws; and the <hi>Protectors</hi> of young Princes muſt give way to the Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of the People. Now the <hi>Catholicks</hi> will not have an Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to bribe us by Civil Securities; the <hi>Church of England</hi> will remember all thoſe <hi>Male adminiſtrations</hi> of his Miniſters, for which they turn'd out King <hi>James;</hi> and will ſay it was the Papiſts hindred us from being redreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt them. And the <hi>Whigs</hi> will throw it in their Diſh, that they offer'd them Friendſhip upon Legal Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and that they did not cry out upon the <hi>Declaration for Indulgence,</hi> tho' founded upon a <hi>Diſpenſing Power,</hi> till the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> flew, or made at leaſt an appearance to fly, at ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of our moſt invaluable <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Privileges.</hi> The <hi>Whigs</hi> will ſay the Papiſts doted upon <hi>French Power,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than <hi>National Reſtauration;</hi> nay, that they ſlighted the laſt, and have every where declared againſt the King's coming home upon <hi>Terms, Conceſſions, Reformations,</hi> and <hi>amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of our Conſtitution; tho' unleſs they had intended to exerciſe a <hi>Daniſh Lordlineſs</hi> over us, their own Welfare muſt have been concluded in every thing that made <hi>England</hi> Happy. It matters not how unjuſt theſe Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions will be: it is a true, tho' a courſe Proverb, <hi>It is eaſie to find a ſtick, when one has a mind to beat a Dog.</hi> Is it the firſt time that we have againſt you believed Lies? I neither am, nor I hope to God ever ſhall be a <hi>Roman Catholick;</hi> but I have ſuch Bowels to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all Mankind, that I ſeriouſly proteſt I have ſuch <hi>melancholly Bodings</hi> far the <hi>Romans Catholick Party,</hi> I fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee ſuch a Period of Calamity (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Human reckoning) falling up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, if the King is not reſtored by <hi>Great Compliances</hi> with his People, and in his own Perſon, that it has gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me many a painful Though: and I muſt confeſs I am infinitely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned for many excellent Perſons of that Communion, who deſerve bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than to be made a Sacrifice to our Rage and Madneſs, who deſerve all the Benefits of Fellow-Subjects. The <hi>Whigs</hi> and <hi>Church of England-men</hi> will come to a <hi>Compromiſe</hi> at that day; but in all Human appearance it will be a dreadful one to the Catholicks. Now they have an Opportunity to be incorporated with the Proteſtants; but if they don't make uſe of it, they may be <hi>pity</hi>'d, but no Man will<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in all probability, be able to <hi>help</hi> them. How <hi>Univerſal</hi> and <hi>Catholick</hi> ſoever their Religion may be in other places, I am ſure they are Fanaticks in <hi>England</hi> under a Civil Conſideration; and therefore that they have all the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the World to be State-Whigs, and as ſuch only will ever be impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially uſed by us.</p>
            <p>I think nothing that I have ſaid has depretiated the Doctrine of <hi>Paſſive-Obedience.</hi> I do not pretend to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine who is in the Right in that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, much leſs to handle it as a Religious One: But give me leave to tell an admirable Story concerning Dr. <hi>Colvil,</hi> a great Man in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:154028:12"/>of <hi>Scotland,</hi> but one that was thought not to underſtand clearly the Principle of <hi>Non-Reſiſtance.</hi> The late Earl of <hi>Middleton</hi> having him once at Dinner, asked him, <hi>Whether there could be no Caſe in which Defenſive Arms were Lawful?</hi> The Doctor replied, <hi>It was fit for the People to believe them unlawful, and for Kings to believe them lawful.</hi> It was an admitable Repar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee upon a ſudden Queſtion: But perhaps, had he thought of it, he would have ſaid likewiſe, <hi>That it is fit for the Miniſters of Kings to believe them lawful too;</hi> and I preſume the preſent Earl of <hi>Middleton</hi> ſet down that addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Inſtruction to the <hi>Apothegm.</hi> For tho', to the eternal ſhame of the Judges who now ſit upon the King's Bench, they violated our Laws in the continuance of his Impriſonment it muſt be allowed, for his everlaſting Honour, that that Noble Lord was as cautious of making the Law the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of his Miniſtry, as if it were <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to riſe up in Arms whenever the Laws were broken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I muſt Anſwer your <hi>Poſtſcript,</hi> wherein you tell me, that you nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther know how the <hi>King</hi> can be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored now the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> is in poſſeſſion; nor what will become of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> if we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the <hi>King;</hi> nor what Security we could have from any Conditions the King could make with us. I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that if the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> is not kept in poſſeſſion by <hi>Engliſh</hi> men, he may ſoon be brought to Reaſon; and I do aſſure you, that there are many <hi>Jacobites</hi> that deſire rather to ſee the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> return to his Station of Stadtholder again in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> than wiſh him any perſonal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury: And as for the Security you require for any promiſed Conditions, you muſt forgive me if I think you a little inſincere, if not trifling, when you place ſo much Weight upon the Pope's giving King <hi>James</hi> an Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for any Promiſes he ſhould make. You might have ſaid this artfully to the Mobb; but you cannot ſuppoſe that I would believe you were in earneſt, though you make ſuch a clutter with it. I allow, as you ſay, that our Hiſtories tell us of ſome Kings that were abſolved by Popes; but you know that <hi>Bulls, Abſolutions,</hi> and the Pope's <hi>Excommunications</hi> were like to go farther with the Nation in Popiſh Times, than they are like to do now: And yet by your very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, you might be convinced, that the People of <hi>England</hi> never would, even then, let a King be at reſt, till he had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed his Promiſes. I will not write a long Confutation of a thing that I know cannot ſtick with you, or any wiſe conſidering Man. And beſides, I do not go about to perſwade you to take up with a Conſtitution, that will depend either upon a <hi>King's Temper</hi> or <hi>Religion, Honour</hi> or <hi>Veracity.</hi> Make a <hi>Government</hi> that is eaſie to all, and it will be the Intereſt of all to preſerve it: But if you would do ſo, you muſt bring the Right Line into it; you muſt nicely preſerve the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as the National Church; and yet you muſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that the Kngdom of Heaven is not of this World: You muſt take care in your Civil Compacts, that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:154028:13"/>
               <hi>Prieſtcraft</hi> does not ſpoyl all at laſt: You muſt take care even of a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, <hi>in Ordine ad Spiritualia;</hi> and let the Tares and the Wheat grow up to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. But farther, although you have ſuch wild accounts concerning the <hi>Jacobites;</hi> there are amongſt thoſe that ſerve King <hi>James,</hi> Men that know what you are a doing; that know you are looking far and near for a Deliverance; that know how impotent you think the Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi> is to Rule; how that you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe him, as much as the Nation miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked <hi>Richard Cremwel</hi> before the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration; that know your extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant Projects, and more tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Thoughts, and yet have accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for all things; and will, as things ripen, find ways to give you ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, if any thing will. We know that <hi>Maud</hi> the Empreſs, even when King <hi>Stephen</hi> was a Priſoner; and though her Title was indiſputable, and though the Nation was all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks, loſt the Crown, becauſe ſhe was refractory and haughty, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to the <hi>Londoners, Edward</hi> the Confeſſor's Laws. And I aſſure you there will be Men that will lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>King</hi> the Neceſſity and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of giving Satisfaction to all your Reaſonable Demands. If you do not ask too much <hi>Counter-ſecurity,</hi> things unfit for an <hi>Engliſh King</hi> to grant, there are <hi>Jacobites</hi> that will not only deliver, but ſecond your Petitions. <hi>A Good and Settled Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi> you may have; and a <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth</hi> is ſcarce <hi>practicable,</hi> will be hazardous at preſent, and cannot be <hi>laſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know there are ſome amongſt the <hi>Jacobites,</hi> who are otherwiſe Men of great <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Worth;</hi> and yet ſuſpect every thing, ſuch as you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote is to make the King a <hi>Doge</hi> of <hi>Venice:</hi> But there are others who have compared, and taken in pieces, and viewed in parts, all the Models of Government; who, if you would rectifie, and not change, either the Name or Nature of ours, will receive very kindly any thing you offer, will inſtruct you how to make it palatable to the King, and ſhew him how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent it is both with his Honour and his Intereſt. Let the manner be <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi> and your Propoſitions allow King <hi>James</hi> to have the <hi>Ballance</hi> that an <hi>Engliſh King</hi> ſhould have, and muſt neceſſarily have in our Conſtitution. And I aſſure you many of the <hi>Jaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites</hi> know no other but ſuch an <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh King</hi> to be our <hi>Supreme Head and Governour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, after all, if King <hi>James</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led home by the Nation, we need no other Security than a <hi>well-choſen</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. The preſent Parliament may call him home when they pleaſe, without any other Force, but their own denial of Money. And the King's being of another Religion, will in ſome meaſure check the effects of a <hi>Revolutionary Joy,</hi> and prevent our <hi>Exceſſes.</hi> And if ſober and honeſt Men would in all Corporations (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of all other Projects) inſtruct all the Populace, That all thoſe that drink upon their Members Coſt, hazard being Slaves for that Draught; and that it is time ſeriouſly to take Care of Themſelves and their Poſterity, by chooſing Men of Virtue, rather than the <hi>Favourites</hi> or the <hi>Factions</hi> of any
<pb facs="tcp:154028:13"/>Opinion, whether they are <hi>Jure Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vino</hi> or <hi>Original Contract men;</hi> Men that are as well Loyal to their Country as their King, and to their King as their Country; Men that have good Nature, Eſtates, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, Senſe, and moderate Minds: Such a Parliament would be an <hi>heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Parliament;</hi> might not only <hi>end,</hi> but take away all occaſions for Strife and Changes. And <hi>Eſtabliſhment, Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> are a <hi>Nobler Happineſs</hi> than <hi>exceſſive Riches, pompous Buildings,</hi> and all the other <hi>Glories</hi> that a People can poſſeſs. How is the Excellency of the <hi>Spartan Inſtitution</hi> every where and every day applauded, tho' all their Pleaſures ſeem to be nothing elſe but Hardſhips and Self-denial? But we may add <hi>Plenty</hi> to our <hi>Peace,</hi> increaſe our <hi>Trade</hi> and our <hi>Strength,</hi> and by our <hi>Naval Force,</hi> and a perfect Union amongſt our ſelves, be again conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as the <hi>Arbiters</hi> of <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I am unawares launching into a ſpacious Subject. It is time to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude. I wiſh all <hi>Engliſh-men</hi> would conſider how to do it; and I wiſh there could ſuddenly, before we are <hi>undone,</hi> a method be found out to <hi>recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile</hi> the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Nephew,</hi> and all his Children, both <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal;</hi> a method found out to adjuſt all our <hi>Intereſts,</hi> and bring us all to our <hi>reſpective Duties.</hi> I beſeech God ſo to order things, that all Sects and ſorts of <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men may think it a <hi>National Good</hi> to reſtore our King. I have read our <hi>Annals;</hi> I wiſh every body had. Could I here delineate the <hi>Scars</hi> and <hi>Woulds,</hi> the <hi>Bloodſheds</hi> and <hi>Diſtreſſes,</hi> that the <hi>Violation</hi> of the <hi>Hereditary Title</hi> (which will hover over all <hi>Uſurpations,</hi> and all Forms of a <hi>Commonwealth</hi>) have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> could I paint out the <hi>Executions,</hi> and <hi>Extinctions</hi> of Noble Families, that the Wars between the <hi>Two Houſes</hi> have occaſioned, they would repreſent but an <hi>horrid Proſpect,</hi> a <hi>doleful Scene.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Oh, Bleſſed God! Viſit not this Land for its Iniquities with Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; but in Judgment remember Mercy. Let Righteouſneſs and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy Reſtore Him to it, and on them eſtabliſh the Throne of thy Servant <hi>JAMES;</hi> Teach Him to go in and out before this great People, which (by our Laws and Oaths, and His In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance) thou haſt committed to His Charge: Let His Children Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, His Subjects Obey, and His Nephew be Juſt to Him, and GOD be Glorified, be ſtill Glorified, in His and Our wonderful Deliverance; that Wickedneſs may no longer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper, but Peace return to us, and our Childrens Children, to all Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
               </q> And God put it into the Hearts of all His Subjects to ſay likewiſe <hi>Amen</hi> to this National and Honeſt Prayer.</p>
            <p>I find that my Letter has grown under my hands; but if it tires you, you muſt thank your ſelf that you ſtarted ſo much <hi>Game;</hi> a great deal has riſen before me in writing that I have not followed, tho' I hope I have writ enough to let you know, that whatever Spirit you find ſome <hi>Jaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites</hi> in, yet there are others that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſguſt a reaſonable Man; and alſo that I am the ſame Engliſh-man you ever knew me, as well as,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>SIR, Your affectionate Friend, and faithful Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:154028:14"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT</head>
            <p>THE Letter I ſent you laſt <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt,</hi> being ſhewn to ſome that are yours as well as my old Friends, and more ſo to <hi>England</hi> than to ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of us, it was, at their importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, ſent to the Preſs, ſoon enough to have been publiſhed long before the Parliament met; but when part of it was Printed, the reſt was ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped by ſome Accidents that are not ſo proper to mention, and therefore ſome ſew Expreſſions of it may not be altogether ſo ſeaſonable as they were when I wrote it to you (ſince the Money is now given;) however I hope in the main it may be of ſome uſe. And now we have begun this Scribling Conflict, I deſire that in your next you will let me know when you can reaſonably ſuppoſe this War, and conſequently Taxes, will end? And whether, if the Conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>deracy ſhould break before you have thought fit to reſtore your Rightful and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful King, or the <hi>French</hi> are more humbled (as you call it) than they are hitherto, we ſhould not indeed run a greater risk of our Liberties, for the preſent, (after ſuch a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued Provocation of the King) than either you, or I, or any good <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> man could wiſh to ſee? Tell me likewiſe, whether thoſe that are not of our Army or Fleet, cannot, if they have a Mind to reſtore the King upon a National Foot, influence thoſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives that are in both, to reſtore King <hi>James,</hi> as the <hi>Old Army</hi> did his Brother. You have read Hiſtory, and know that an Army of Natives follows the inclinations of the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants; you know the real Power your Party has in the Nation; and that it is not the <hi>Tories,</hi> who have broke in upon their own <hi>Conſciences,</hi> but you, who have <hi>forſaken</hi> your <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings,</hi> that keep the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> (as much as you every day ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicule him) from being ſent for good and all to <hi>Holland;</hi> and though you do not know how to make him either value <hi>your Perſons,</hi> or ſee <hi>his own Intereſt;</hi> yet you can ſoon find ways (notwithſtanding your own La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude) to make an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon their <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Obligations</hi> to King <hi>James,</hi> and their Uſage un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this Man; nay, you cannot but know they begin themſelves to have theſe Reflections, and therefore with very little pains you may prepare them Nationally to Reſtore the King; which if they do (with all due regard to him be it ſpoken) he is, as it were, in our Power, and he muſt grant thoſe Conceſſions we really want; and where a King, whoſe Title is indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pured, frankly hears Advice from a <hi>duly-elected Parliament,</hi> the genuine and united Senſe of the Nation may be gathered up, and a Natural Cure given to all our Troubles, and only from thence can come an impartial Settlement. Think of theſe things ſeriouſly, and let not the Diſcourſes of ſuch <hi>Jacobites,</hi> as you complain of,
<pb facs="tcp:154028:14"/>(who have as little Intereſt with the <hi>Kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> as you ſay they have with <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) either give you diſturbance, or make you any long<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r willing to undergo worſe things under this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation,</hi> than you can have any juſt reaſon to fear, if the King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns; eſpecia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly, if you your ſelves Reſtore him. Beſides, I muſt tell you, I have good reaſon to believe, the King of <hi>France</hi> himſelf (with whom you fright the <hi>Mob</hi>) is not politically an Enemy to a limited Monarchy in <hi>England;</hi> and that he will agree to a reaſonable Peace in <hi>Europe,</hi> if the Reſtauration of King <hi>James</hi> is made one of the Conditions of it; and that he will not be brought to any Peace unleſs we Reſtore him, how much ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> has flatter'd you, that (inſtead of the Vineyards and Spoils of <hi>Paris,</hi> that he ſeemed to promiſe) <hi>he will bring him to an honourable Peace.</hi> I will only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> That whereas ſome of your Party do now, as you did formerly, raiſe mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and unjuſt Calumnies upon the Queen; I am fully ſatisfied that ſhe is as deſirous the King ſhould comply with his People, as the Nobleſt and niceſt Patriots could be, were King <hi>James</hi> upon the Throne: She has a mind that the Struggles between the <hi>Crown</hi> and the <hi>People</hi> ſhould be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſted, that ſo the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of her <hi>Son</hi> may be ſecured. Think of all this ſeriouſly, write me your mind freely, and act as becomes a true Lover of <hi>England.</hi> Be not over fond of your own Creation, as a <hi>Williamite.</hi> Meddle not with thoſe who world yet farther change the <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of our Government, and then (fiercely as you are ſo now) be <hi>Anti-Jacobite</hi> as long as you can. Once again, Adieu.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>DEdication, line 12. for ever, r. <hi>even.</hi> Pag. 6. col. 1. l. 40. r. <hi>Incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> Pag. 9. col. 2. l. 9. after this, add <hi>part.</hi> Pag. 11. col. 2. l. 6. af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter prove, add <hi>to.</hi> l. 33. after time, add <hi>in.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:154028:15"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154028:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
